Guide to the Reynolds Price Papers, 1927-2010 and undated, bulk 1956-2006
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Reynolds Price papers 1927-2010 and undated, bulk 1956-2006
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Price, Reynolds, 1933-2011
198.7 linear feet Extent: 96,900 Items
Reynolds Price was a novelist, short story writer, poet, dramatist, essayist, translator, and James B. Duke Professor of English at Duke University, where he taught creative writing and literature beginning in 1958. He was an alumnus of Duke and of Oxford University, which he attended on a Rhodes Scholarship. He received fellowships from the Guggenheim Foundation and the National Endowment for the Arts, and his books were nominated for the Pulitzer Prize and the National Book Award. Correspondence, writings, serials, clippings, speeches, interviews, legal and financial papers, photographs, audiovisual materials, and digital materials about Price's career and personal life. Personal and professional correspondence document his education at Duke University, especially his studies under William Blackburn; his period abroad as a Rhodes Scholar at Merton College, Oxford; and his literary work and interaction with other authors, including Stephen Spender, Eudora Welty, and Allan Gurganus. Writings include manuscripts, typescripts, proofs, outlines, and notes produced in the creation and publication of all his major works, including: A Long and Happy Life; Kate Vaiden; A Palpable God; Clear Pictures; A Whole New Life; The Collected Stories; The Collected Poems; and many other books and individual stories, poems, and essays. Printed and audiovisual materials document the critical reception of Price's work and his speeches, readings, interviews, and many other public appearances.
Later additions are described in detail below.
pricereynolds
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Also, original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Use copies are available in the collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Reynolds Price Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1986-2006.
Biographical Note
Chronology List
1933 Feb. 1 Born in Macon, NC, to William Solomon and Elizabeth (Rodwell) Price
1954-1955 Editor, The Archive; Advisory editor, Shenandoah at Duke University
1955 A.B. Summa cum laude, Duke University; Angier Duke Scholar
1958 B. Litt. (Rhodes Scholar), Merton College, Oxford University D. Litt., St. Andrew's Presbyterian College
1958- Member of English Department faculty, Duke University
1961-1968 Assistant Professor, Duke University
1962 A Long and Happy Life, first novel and book
1965 Writer-in-residence, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
1967, 1969 Writer-in-residence, University of Kansas
1968-1972 Associate professor, Duke University
1971 Writer-in-residence, University of North Carolina at Greensboro Glasgow Professor, Washington and Lee University
1972-1977 Professor, Duke University
1973-1977 Literature Advisory Panel, National Endowment for the Arts (Chair, 1976)
1977 Faculty, Salzburg Seminar
1977- James B. Duke Professor of English, Duke University
1979 National Book Award nomination for translation, for A Palpable God
1986 National Book Critics Circle Award for Fiction, for Kate Vaiden
1994 Finalist for Pulitzer Prize in fiction, for The Collected Stories
1997 The Collected Poems
2011 Jan. 20 Died following a heart attack, Durham, NC
Collection Overview
The Reynolds Price Papers span the years 1927-2010, with the bulk of the papers being dated between 1956 and 2004. The collection consists of correspondence; writings by Price and other authors; printed material (including serials containing articles by and about Price and his work as well as newspaper and magazine clippings); legal and financial papers; speeches and addresses; interviews; photographs; audiovisual materials; digital materials; and other material relating to Price's personal life and career as a writer and a teacher, especially at Duke University. Although the correspondence does provide insight into his career as an English professor, the collection contains only a small amount of material, such as lecture notes and syllabi, relating to the courses he taught. Extensive personal and professional correspondence between Price and his family, friends, and fellow authors provides insight into his education at Duke University (particularly his studies with Professor William Blackburn of the Department of English); his period abroad as a Rhodes Scholar at Merton College, Oxford; and his literary work.
Many forms of Price's writings (manuscripts, typescripts, stages of proofs with notes, and outlines) document his development of well-known and critically-acclaimed works in a variety of genres: the novels A Long and Happy Life and Kate Vaiden; the Biblical translations collected in A Palpable God; the memoirs Clear Pictures and A Whole New Life; the two career retrospective volumes published in the 1990s, The Collected Stories and The Collected Poems; and many other books and individual stories, poems, and essays. In addition to Price's own work, numerous American authors--particularly Southern writers--and several British authors are represented in the collection. Among the major correspondents are Eudora Welty, Stephen Spender, and Allan Gurganus. Some manuscripts sent to Price by students and by other authors have notations and criticism by Price.
The Correspondence Series (RESTRICTED) is divided into the General Correspondence Subseries and the Authors' Correspondence Subseries. The General Correspondence Series consists of letters to and from Price. Correspondents include family, friends, teachers, and admirers of his work. Early letters vividly depict his relationships with family members and friends. Many of the letters dated between 1954 and 1958 concern his education at Duke University and as a Rhodes Scholar at Merton College, Oxford University. His early development as an author is documented here as well as in the Writings Series. From 1961 onward, letters also provide information about his career as a professor at Duke University. The Authors' Correspondence Subseries comprises correspondence between Price and other writers and literary figures. These letters concern both personal and literary matters. Frequently the correspondents commented on each other's recent publications or on work in progress. Numerous letters to and from Eudora Welty and Stephen Spender reveal much about their strong influence on Price's development as a writer. The series also contains a great many letters from Allan Gurganus, Jeff Humphries, Josephine Humphreys, Joe Porter, Lee Smith, and William Blackburn.
The Writings Series (RESTRICTED) is divided into the Writings by Price Subseries and the Writings by Others Subseries. The former is comprised chiefly of drafts, typescripts, and proofs of Price's novels, plays, autobiographical works, and volumes of poetry, many with Price's notations and revisions, and provides a thorough representation of the development of each. Individual poems, short stories, essays, articles, and reviews by Price are also included. Manuscripts (some of them photocopies) sent to Price by fellow authors and by students make up the Writings by Others Subseries. A few of these include commentary by Price. Both published and unpublished works of poetry and prose are included. A few bibliographies of Price's work are arranged at the end of this series.
The Printed Material Series is divided into the Serials Subseries, the Clippings Subseries, and the Miscellaneous Printed Material Subseries (RESTRICTED). The Serials Subseries is an extensive collection of publications containing articles, reviews, fiction, and poetry by Price as well as articles about him, interviews with him, and reviews of his work. The Clippings Subseries is composed predominantly of reviews of Price's works and other articles about him, but also contains some interviews and short nonfiction work by him, mainly book reviews. Other printed materials documenting Price's achievements, his education, and performances of his dramatic work as well as his speaking engagements are housed in the Miscellaneous Printed Material Subseries.
Several smaller series make up the remainder of the collection. The Legal and Financial Papers Series (RESTRICTED) contains Price's personal financial data as well as documentation of his writing career through contracts and royalty statements. Transcripts of his speeches and interviews appear in the Speeches and Addresses Series (RESTRICTED) and in the Interviews Series (RESTRICTED). The Personal Papers Series (RESTRICTED) contains a small selection of materials about Price and his family history, including some of his drawings, and his teaching career in the Duke University English Department is documented by the Academic Files Series (RESTRICTED). The Photographic Materials Series (RESTRICTED) touches upon both his personal and professional life; of particular interest here are a number of photographs of Eudora Welty, a friend of Price's since his undergraduate days. The Audiovisual Materials Series (RESTRICTED) contains audio and video recordings of a variety of public appearances, including readings, speeches, awards ceremonies, and interviews on various local and national radio and television programs. A small Electronic Formats Series (RESTRICTED) contains files that supplement materials in other series, mainly Price's writings and some correspondence.
Finally, of special note is a large collection of Oversize Materials (RESTRICTED) that supplements material found in most of the major series. This part of the collection is particularly rich in one area, and should not be overlooked by scholars researching the writing, editing and publishing process of any of Price's books up through the early 1990s. The significance of that date lies in the increasing use of photographic and electronic media in the publishing industry. Prior to this time, many of the various kinds of long galley proofs historically used by publishers are housed with the Oversize Materials; after this period, most proofs are printed on legal or even letter-sized paper and can thus be found with the main body of the Writings by Price Series.
The 2007 addition (2007-0009) (4850 items; 10.5 lin. ft.) (dated 2003-2006) primarily consists of typescripts, drafts, and proofs for The Good Priest's Son, Letter to a Godchild, A Serious Way of Wondering, and the screenplay for A Long and Happy Life. Also included is correspondence, personal documents, photographs, bookcovers, and printed materials by other authors.
Addition (2009-0105) (12 items; 0.6 lin. ft.) consists largely of books from Price's writing, teaching, and research, including some text books as well as novels with his notes in the margins. Also included is one folder of miscellaneous notes and correspondence, 1972-1994.
Addition (2011-0013) (9000 items; 12.0 lin. ft.) consists of drafts, revisions, additions, and other materials from writing and publication of Ardent Spirits, Price's 2009 memoir about his time at Oxford University and his early teaching career at Duke. Other writings and drafts in this addition include A Long and Happy Life, Letter to a Godchild, and Clear Pictures. The remainder of the addition is sorted into teaching materials, events, correspondence, and miscellaneous material, including photographs, newspaper clippings, and a disassembled scrapbook.
Addition (2011-0080) (20,000 items; 31.5 lin. ft.) includes writings, correspondence teaching materials, family scrapbooks and albums, personal snapshots, portraits, and other ephemera from Price's home. Includes drafts of Ardent Spirits as well as some short stories and poems. Also includes books from Price's library, several with inscriptions or notes.
Related Material
Materials related to the life and career of Reynolds Price appear in several other collections housed at the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library. The Clear Pictures Film Footage Collection houses materials created and used by Charles Guggenheim in making his 1994 documentary film about Price's life (based on Price's own 1989 memoir of the same title). The collection includes many materials that do not appear in the published version of the film: research, film footage of interviews of and about Price, and electronic files. Documentation of Price's professional writing career appears in the records of the Harriet Wasserman Literary Agency Records. Materials there include correspondence, drafts and published versions of his works, and publishing contracts both with this agency and with Russell and Volkening, Wasserman's employer prior to forming her own agency. Extensive documentation of Price's publishing history can be found in the Jody Jones Hunter Collection of Works by Reynolds Price. In addition to copies of Price's books with major commercial publishers, the Hunter collection also contains many small press publications, limited editions, periodicals, and audiovisual materials. Finally, the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library contains copies of many publications similar to those in the Hunter collection. These items, cataloged separately from the Reynolds Price Papers, are searchable by individual title in the Duke University Libraries online catalog.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Price, Reynolds, 1933-2011; Price family; Blackburn, William (William Maxwell), 1899-1972; Gurganus, Allan, 1947-; Spender, Stephen, 1909-; Welty, Eudora, 1909-; Duke University -- Faculty.; Duke University. Dept. of English.; Merton College.; University of Oxford.; College teachers -- North Carolina -- Correspondence.; Authors, American -- 20th century -- Correspondence.; American literature -- 20th century.; American literature -- Southern States.; Authors, American -- Southern States.; Authors, American -- 20th century.; Essays -- 20th century; Literature -- History and criticism.; Poetry -- 20th century; Rhodes scholarships.; Short stories -- 20th century; Black-and-white photographs.; Color photographs.; Audio cassettes; Videocassettes; Clippings; Outlines; Poems; Proofs; Speeches; Typescripts; Machine-readable records.
Detailed Description of Collection
- Correspondence Series (RESTRICTED), 1936-2004 and undated, (64 boxes)
  Arranged into General Correspondence and Authors' Correspondence subseries.
  [RESTRICTED: during Price's lifetime and twenty years thereafter, access to, and duplication by any means, of materials in this series requires prior written permission from him or his literary executors.]
  - General Correspondence Subseries (RESTRICTED), 1936-2004 and undated, (56 boxes)
    Includes letters from friends, family members, publishers, teachers, students, and readers of Price's works. Most letters are written to Price, with two exceptions: the letters written between 1944 and 1958 include juvenilia and many letters from Price to his family while he studied at Duke and Oxford; and beginning in the late 1990s, printouts of many of Price's emails begin to appear in the files.
    Arranged chronologically, with one exception. Although undated letters would normally be filed at the end of the range of years, the undated letters that appear in Box GC30 have been left where they are because they had already been received when the Price papers were first fully processed circa 1993. Thus, although undated per se, they are known to date prior to 1993 or earlier. The undated letters in Box GC56 at the end of the subseries, on the other hand, have been received by the library from Price since the mid-1990s; thus their actual date of posting may be any time in that period or earlier.
    [RESTRICTED: during Price's lifetime and twenty years thereafter, access to, and duplication by any means, of materials in this subseries requires prior written permission from him or his literary executors.]
    - 1936-1955 Oct., (12 folders) (Box GC1)
    - 1955 Nov.-1956 Dec., (15 folders) (Box GC2)
    - 1957 Jan.-1958 June, (12 folders) (Box GC3)
    - 1958 July-1960 Dec., (11 folders) (Box GC4)
    - 1961 Jan.-1963 Sept., (11 folders) (Box GC5)
    - 1963 Oct.-1966 Mar., (11 folders) (Box GC6)
    - 1966 Apr.-1968 Sept., (13 folders) (Box GC7)
    - 1968 May-1970 Feb., (13 folders) (Box GC8)
    - 1970 Mar.-1971 June, (11 folders) (Box GC9)
    - 1971 July-1972 May, (10 folders) (Box GC10)
    - 1972 June-1973 Aug., (13 folders) (Box GC11)
    - 1973 Sept.-1974 Oct., (12 folders) (Box GC12)
    - 1974 Nov.-1976 Feb. 13, (14 folders) (Box GC13)
    - 1976 Feb. 16-1977 Mar., (12 folders) (Box GC14)
    - 1977 Apr.-1978 May, (14 folders) (Box GC15)
    - 1978 June-1979 Oct., (16 folders) (Box GC16)
    - 1979 Nov.-1981 Mar., (17 folders) (Box GC17)
    - 1981 Apr.-1982 Apr., (13 folders) (Box GC18)
    - 1982 May-1983 May, (14 folders) (Box GC19)
    - 1983 June-1984 June 11, (13 folders) (Box GC20)
    - 1984 June 12-1985 Mar., (12 folders) (Box GC21)
    - 1985 Apr.-1986 Aug., (17 folders) (Box GC22)
    - 1986 Sept.-1987 May, (11 folders) (Box GC23)
    - 1987 June-1988 May, (12 folders) (Box GC24)
    - 1988 June-1989 May, (12 folders) (Box GC25)
    - 1989 June-1990 Feb., (12 folders) (Box GC26)
    - 1990 Mar.- Nov., (11 folders) (Box GC27)
    - 1990 Dec.-1991 Aug., (14 folders) (Box GC28)
    - 1991 Aug.-1992 May, (13 folders) (Box GC29)
    - 1992 June- Dec. and undated, (12 folders) (Box GC30)
    - 1992 Jan. 7-circa 1992 and Christmas cards, (18 folders) (Box GC31)
    - 1993 Jan. 3-June 15, (18 folders) (Box GC32)
    - 1993 June 16-circa 1993 and Christmas cards, (19 folders) (Box GC33)
    - 1994 Jan. 1-June 22, (14 folders) (Box GC34)
    - 1994 June 28-Oct. 9, (14 folders) (Box GC35)
    - 1994 Oct. 10-1995 Jan. 10, (13 folders) (Box GC36)
    - 1995 Jan. 11-Apr. 19, (13 folders) (Box GC37)
    - 1995 Apr. 20-July 9, (11 folders) (Box GC38)
    - 1995 July 10-Sept. 24, (11 folders) (Box GC39)
    - 1995 Sept. 25-Dec. 12, (11 folders) (Box GC40)
    - 1995 Dec. 13-1996 Feb. 6, (10 folders) (Box GC41)
    - 1996 Feb. 7-Apr. 19, (9 folders) (Box GC42)
    - 1996 Apr. 20-July 9, (10 folders) (Box GC43)
    - 1996 July 10-Oct. 31, (9 folders) (Box GC44)
    - 1996 Nov. 1-1997 Feb. 28, (12 folders) (Box GC45)
    - 1997 Mar. 3-Aug. 22, (11 folders) (Box GC46)
    - 1997 Aug. 24-1997 Dec. 31, (10 folders) (Box GC47)
    - 1998 Jan. 1-July 31, (10 folders) (Box GC48)
    - 1998 Aug. 1 -1998 Dec. 31, (11 folders) (Box GC49)
    - 1999 Jan. 1-Sept. 30, (10 folders) (Box GC50)
    - 1999 Oct. 1-2000 Apr. 28, (9 folders) (Box GC51)
    - 2000 May-2001 Jan., (10 folders) (Box GC52)
    - 2001 Feb.-2002 Mar., (15 folders) (Box GC53)
    - 2002 Apr.-2003 May, (15 folders) (Box GC54)
    - 2003 June-2004 May and undated, (14 folders) (Box GC55)
    - Undated, (9 folders) (Box GC56)
  - Authors' Correspondence Subseries (RESTRICTED), 1940-2004 and undated, (8 boxes)
    Consists of letters from literary figures who wrote to Price regarding his work or their own.
    Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by the last name of the author, then chronologically within the folder. Letters from Price to particular authors are filed under the recipient's name. An exception to this arrangement is the final box of the series, which consists of correspondence between Price and various members of the American Academy of Arts and Letters. The content is generally brief discussion and opinion about the work of other writers being considered for various awards by the Academy. These folders are arranged chronologically.
    - A-B, 1953-2003 and undated, (21 folders) ENTIRE BOX IS RESTRICTED. (Box AC1)
      - Abbott, Shirley, 1986, (1 item)
      - Adcock, Betty, 1996-2003, (12 items)
      - Albee, Edward, 1963-1981 and undated, (5 items)
      - Applewhite, Jim, 1970-1998, (11 items)
      - Athas, Daphne, 1971-2002 and undated, (25 items)
      - Auden, Wystan H., 1960 and undated, (3 items)
      - Bayes, Ron, 1969-1985, (43 items)
      - Bell, Madison Smartt, 1999-2000, (5 items)
      - Betts, Doris, 1970-1990, (28 items)
      - Bingham, Sallie, 1998-2000, (4 items)
      - Blackburn, William and family, 1953-2002 and undated, (111 items)
      - Bly Robert, 1998, (1 item)
      - Brondoli, Michael, 1972-1986 and undated, (41 letters)
      - Brooks, Cleanth, 1964-1990, (11 letters)
      - Broughton, T. Alan, 1968-1991, (24 items)
      - Brown, Lightning, 1995, (4 folders)
      - Buechner, Frederick, 1969-2000, (23 items)
    - B-G, 1956-2003 and undated, (31 folders) ENTIRE BOX IS RESTRICTED. (Box AC2)
      - Busch, Frederick, 1969-1991 and undated, (95 items)
      - Carr, Virginia, 2002-2003, (7 items)
      - Campbell, Alan, 1958-1962, (5 items)
      - Cecil, David and family, 1956-1990 and undated, (59 items)
      - Chappell, Fred, 1961-1990 and undated, (18 items)
      - Coles, Robert, 1993-1994, (7 items)
      - Conroy, Pat, 1989, (3 items)
      - Corn, Alfred, 1988-1990, (12 items)
      - Cowley, Malcolm, 1972-1975, (3 items)
      - Cox, Elizabeth, 1979-2002, (19 items)
      - Crews, Harry, 1971, (1 item)
      - Davidson, Cathy, 1994-1999, (3 items)
      - de Buys, William, 1993-1994, (2 items)
      - Dickey, James, 1968-2001, (12 items)
      - Dillard, Annie 1995-1998 and undated, (4 items)
      - Douglas, Ellen (Josephine Harton), 1981-1982, (4 items)
      - Edgerton, Clyde, 1990-1999, (4 items)
      - Ellison, Ralph, 1964-1974, (7 items)
      - Foote, Horton, 1984-2002 and undated, (38 items)
      - Ford, Richard, 1995-2003, (10 items)
      - Fort, Charles, 1992-1993, (2 items)
      - Franklin, John Hope, 1994, (1 item)
      - Gibbons, Kaye, 1989-1999 and undated, (6 items)
      - Gilchrist, Ellen, 1978-1997, (5 items)
      - Grimsley, Jim, 1999, (1 item)
      - Gordimer, Nadine, 1999, (2 items)
      - Gurganus, Allan, 1974-2002 and undated, (96 items)
      - Guy, David, 1971-2002, (13 items)
    - H-K, 1958-2003 and undated, (19 folders) ENTIRE BOX IS RESTRICTED. (Box AC3)
      - Hannah, Barry, 1987, (2 items)
      - Harrison, Jim, 1973, (2 items)
      - Haydn, Hiram, 1958-1973, (63 items)
      - Hays, Tommy 1999-2002, (4 items)
      - Henly, Beth, 1988-1990, (5 items)
      - Humphries, Jeff, 1977-1997, (68 items)
      - Humphreys, Josephine, 1967-2002 and undated, (83 items)
      - Isherwood, Christopher, 1977, (1 item)
      - Kaufman, Wallace, 1958-2003 and undated, (314 items)
      - Kimmel, Haven, 2001, (1 item)
      - Kizer, Carolyn, 1972-1994 and undated, (39 letters)
    - K-P 1959-2003 and undated, (31 folders) ENTIRE BOX IS RESTRICTED. (Box AC4)
      - Knowles, John, 1963-1969, (72 letters)
      - Kramer, Larry, 1999-2000, (2 items)
      - Kreyling, Michael, 1978-2001 and undated, (57 items)
      - Kushner, Tony, 1999, (1 item)
      - Levertov, Denise, 1972, (1 letter)
      - Linney, Romulus, 1965-2003 and undated, (66 items)
      - MacLeish, Roderick, 1994, (1 item)
      - Mailer, Norman, 1977, 1984, (2 items)
      - Malone, Michael, 2000 and undated, (3 items)
      - Malouf, Melissa, 2003, (1 item)
      - Maron, Margaret, 1994, (1 item)
      - Maxwell, William, 1997-2000, (2 item)
      - McFee, Michael, 1993-1994, (5 items)